Finding Aid for Whitehead family papers, 1862-1900
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Whitehead family papers 1862-1900
Whitehead family
0.3 linear feet
85490 Aa 2
Papers of the Edward and Nellie Wilson Whitehead family of Coldwater, Branch County, Michigan. Family letters largely concerning daily activities, including occasional mention of land prices, social customs, fashions and health problems.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from Oakland University (donor no. 5740 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Whitehead family resided in Coldwater, Michigan.
The collection of the Whitehead family of Coldwater, Michigan consists entirely of letters from family and friends. The correspondence centers around Edward and Nellie Wilson Whitehead, chiefly from Nellie Whitehead's sisters Lucy Wilson Gifford Smith, Leothie Wilson Culver, Orpha Wilson, and Laura Wilson, and her cousins Mary and Naomi Baker. The bulk of the letters were written in the 1870's when Edward and Nellie Whitehead were living in Webster and Churchville, New York. There are, however, a few earlier letters (the first being in 1862) as well as some later in the 1880's. With the last composed in 1900. The letters are all of a general type with an occasional passage discussing land prices and conditions, fashions of the days health problems, etc. The majority speak of family concerns-neighborhood and family gossip. The correspondence came from Angola, Indiana; Battle Creek, Batavia, Coldwater, Jackson, and Sturgis, Michigan; and Batavia, Churchville, and Webster, New York, with the largest share, naturally, coming from Michigan.
Subjects:
Branch County (Mich.); Coldwater (Mich.); Michigan--Social life and customs--1871-1880.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1881-1890.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; Women--Michigan--Coldwater.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.
Contributors:
Whitehead, Edward.; Whitehead, Nellie Wilson.
- Family papers
  - Nellie (Ellen) Wilson (letters to), 1862-1870 (Box 1)
  - Edward and Nellie Whitehead, letters exchanged with Wilson and Whitehead families
    - 1870s, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1871-1874 (Box 1)
    - 1876-1878 (Box 1)
    - 1879-1881, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1885-1900 (Box 1)
  - Nellie Whitehead (letters from)
    - Baker family, 1871-1876 (Box 1)
    - Friends, 1871-1876 (Box 1)
    - Laura Gibbs, 1871-1879 (?) (Box 1)
  - Carrie Sampson from Ellen Whitehead, 1873-1880 (Box 1)
    (Ellen Whitehead is the sister-in-law of Nellie Whitehead and the sister of Edward Whitehead.)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1866-1900 (Box 1)
  - Appointment of W. H. Shaw to hospital steward of Sixth Regiment of Michigan Volunteer Artillery, 1863 (Box 1)